[Music]
hello this is chef john from
foodwishes.com with
quick chicken couscous that's right
right not only is this very fast and
easy
it's also beautiful delicious and
incredibly versatile
and will work with almost any
ingredients and why this stuff isn't way
more popular
is one of the great culinary mysteries i
mean once you have everything prepped
which doesn't take very long at all
we're talking about having a truly
gorgeous meal ready in about 10 or 15
minutes
i know it sounds too good to be true but
it is and to get started we're going to
measure exactly one and a half cups of
whole wheat couscous into this bowl
and contrary to popular belief couscous
is not a grain
it's actually a very very tiny whole
wheat pasta
and by the way there's actually two
types regular and quick cooking
or instant and we definitely want to use
the quick cooking kind for this
and then to our couscous we will add
some salt as well as some freshly ground
pepper and a few shakes of cayenne
followed by three tablespoons of olive
oil which is one of the big keys to the
whole operation
and what we'll do is take a spoon and
give this a thorough mixing until each
and every one of those little tiny
grains of pasta
is coated with the oil and once we're
100 positive that's been accomplished
we will finish by leveling off and
smoothing out the top
and just in case you're not familiar
with how this works all we need to do to
cook this
quote unquote is to pour in a cup of
boiling liquid
usually some kind of flavorful broth at
which point we cover it
wait five minutes and then we eat and
that's it it really is that simple
which reminds me make sure you tear off
a piece of foil big enough to cover this
bowl
since as soon as we pour in our hot
broth we are going to need to cover this
immediately
so make sure you have that ready and
that's it once our couscous bowl has
been prepped
we can move on to a totally optional
step and that would be to season the
chicken breast on both sides with salts
and then searing it over high heat and a
little bit of olive oil
in the same saucepan we're going to use
to boil our broth
oh and if you're going to include
something like red onions which i am
and you want to give those a little bit
of a head start we will bring those over
to the stove as well
and all we're going to do here is give
this chicken breast a quick sear
since meat that's browned always has a
little more flavor but as you'll see
it's also going to form a little bit of
a fond on the bottom of the pan
which means even more flavor going into
our broth once we heat that up
so we'll go ahead and sear that first
side for about two or three minutes
at which point we will toss in our
onions and we'll saute those for a few
minutes while our second side browns
and no i have no idea what that
mysterious slash is
okay i didn't get anywhere close to this
with a knife so i'm guessing whoever at
the factory took off the skin
must have nicked it or at least that's
what i hope it was
but anyway once we browned our chicken
breast for a few minutes on both sides
and we've taken the raw edge off those
onions we'll remove everything from the
heat
and we will transfer that into a bowl to
cool before we cube it up
and i could have left the onions in the
pan but i wanted you guys to get a great
look at that fond
which is that beautiful caramelization
that happens when you sear something in
a pan
and that even though we only cooked our
chicken for a few minutes is going to
provide a lot of extra flavor
speaking of which let's go ahead and
transfer in that one cup of liquid i
mentioned
earlier which in my case is a nice rich
chicken broth
and then we'll follow that with whatever
vegetables we're going to include
which for me is going to be some diced
zucchini some sliced green beans
some diced sweet red pepper and then a
little bit of freshly sliced green
onions
and the reason we want to cut this stuff
nice and small is because we pretty much
want this stuff tender
by the time our broth reaches a boil
which is only going to take a few
minutes as you will see
so that's looking good and at this point
we'll go back and cut up our chicken
which i'm going to do by cutting it into
strips lengthwise
and then we'll turn it and cut across
into like half inch pieces
and i should mention you can also use
thighs for this and it will work out
just about the same
or which is even a more common way for
me to make this you can use cut up
leftover cooked chicken
which obviously saves you a whole step
so keep this in mind the next time you
roast chicken if you have some leftovers
this recipe is definitely something you
should be eating the next day
and that's it once our chicken's been
cut up we will add that along with our
onions to the rest of the ingredients
at which point we are ready to finish
off our quick chicken couscous
so we'll go ahead and place this over
high heat and we will wait for that to
begin to simmer
and while we do we can toss in any other
spices or seasonings we feel like
which for me was a little touch of
smoked paprika plus a little bit of
turmeric
which not only fights every major
disease it's also going to give our
couscous an even more beautiful color
right we used to call that poor man
saffron when it was okay to use
expressions like that
but anyway we'll go ahead and stir that
in and like i said we'll wait for this
to start simmering
and once it does we'll give it a quick
stir and then maybe wait one more minute
for it to come to a full boil and by
then
because we diced our vegetables small
and our chicken was also in nice small
pieces
by the time this is boiling everything
should be just barely cooked
so once boiling we will pull this off
the heat and we will safely but very
quickly dump it into our couscous
but we are not going to stir right we're
just going to toss it in
quickly spread it out and then wrap it
with foil okay immediately and very very
tightly
and then as soon as that's wrapped we
will set our timer for exactly five
minutes
and then once our timer rings we'll go
ahead and unwrap this
and we will toss in some freshly chopped
parsley and or the fresh herbs of your
choice
and then we'll take a spoon and give
everything a stir and because every
little piece of couscous was coated in
olive oil
as we break this up while we stir every
little particle of couscous will
separate
and it will take on a very light and
fluffy texture
and of course before serving you have to
taste and adjust for salt
as it often needs another pinch which
mine did
so i went ahead and added some stirred
it in and gave it another taste
and then once we're happy with that
we'll go ahead and serve it up
and then i like to garnish with some
crumbled feta but a nice garlicky yogurt
sauce would also be beautiful
or maybe something like a zotziki so as
usual final garnishing is up to you
and i ended up finishing mine with some
chili flakes a little more freshly
chopped parsley
and a final drizzle of olive oil and
that's it our quick chicken couscous is
ready to enjoy
and that my friends for something that
only takes a few minutes to prep
and literally five minutes to cook
really does make for an incredibly
impressive meal
right that couscous is satisfying and
filling while at the same time being
fairly light
and because our chicken pieces were only
briefly cooked they should be moist and
tender
and what i love about this recipe
besides everything is that we can do
this with so many different kinds of
vegetables
okay as long as they're diced small or
pre-cooked a little bit like the onions
they're gonna work perfectly in this so
i really do hope you adapt this to your
tastes
i mean you are after all the dr seuss of
your couscous
and this really is a perfect dish for
personal variations and adaptations
oh and speaking of being versatile this
is wonderful hot
magnificent warm fantastic room temp
and you can even chill it and bring it
to a picnic as a salad
which in that case i like to splash in a
little bit of vinegar or maybe squeeze
in some fresh lemon
and it really is delicious chilled but
anyway
that's it what we're calling quick
chicken couscous
if you're ready to take a little bit of
a break from pasta rice and potatoes
i think this makes for a great change of
pace but whether you need your pace
changed or not
i really do hope you give this a try
soon so please follow the links below
for the ingredient amounts
a printable written recipe and much more
info as usual
and as always enjoy
you